<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teakettle Labs</title>
    <description>Teakettle Labs - Making NLP development more equitable and inclusive by raising awareness of bias and enabling actionable change.</description>
    <link>https://teakettlelabs.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://teakettlelabs.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 22:54:32 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 22:54:32 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fluency vs Understanding</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2022/09/29/concrete-harms-of-llms.html&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; we talked about how Large Language Models (LLMs) can be biased and the harms that they can cause, but now it’s useful to delve into some of the details of how exactly LLMs work, how people use them, and why it can be a problem if we ascribe more accuracy and authority to them than they warrant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fluency-understanding-and-how-llms-work&quot;&gt;Fluency, Understanding, and How LLMs Work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LLMs are AI models that deal with language, which is an incredibly complex aspect of human behavior, culture, and understanding that involves quite a lot of nuance and context. We as humans often struggle to understand one another, so asking LLMs to do so is quite a tall order. LLMs have grown much more powerful over the past few years, however, and often seem like they actually are understanding human language. The big issue here, however, is separating fluency from actual understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fluency comes from being very good at patterns and guessing what might come next in a sequence. A fluent model can produce language that sounds natural and has correct grammar and word usage, making it easy for a human to read. Understanding on the other hand is actually much more complex and comes from an underlying knowledge of concepts, intent, meaning, and cross-relations. If a black box is fluent enough, humans are good at extrapolating an assumption of understanding, regardless of whether the model itself has any actual understanding. &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.18653/v1/2020.acl-main.463&quot;&gt;Bender and Koller (2020)&lt;/a&gt; have argued that a model trained only on &lt;em&gt;form&lt;/em&gt; and not &lt;em&gt;meaning&lt;/em&gt; cannot learn &lt;em&gt;meaning&lt;/em&gt;, even if there is a &lt;strong&gt;lot&lt;/strong&gt; of &lt;em&gt;form&lt;/em&gt;. The typical way LLMs are trained is by using huge (generally unlabeled) datasets where the models pick up all they know simply via the form of the data without any connection to further context, which leads to models that are trained to be fluent and focus on patterns, not to express understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, a lot of the current work on language models can trace its roots back to a famous quote in the history of linguistics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You shall know a word by the company it keeps (Firth, J. R. 1957)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, in turn, is based on an older quote often attributed to Aesop about the character of a person being judged by the company they keep. If we think about the Aesop version for a moment, we might feel a bit of social discomfort about it. To the ears of our more modern sensibilities, it feels like an unfair snap judgment to decide how we view someone based solely on their friends and acquaintances rather than on who they are as a multi-faceted person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same is true of words. Training form is scalable and tractable, so we do it, but words, concepts, and languages are multi-faceted too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.18653/v1/P16-2096&quot;&gt;The Social Impact of Natural Language Processing&lt;/a&gt; (Hovy &amp;amp; Spruit, 2016), a point is made that language is always &lt;em&gt;situated&lt;/em&gt;, that is to say that language, as a proxy for human behavior, is uttered in a specific situation, at a particular place and time, and by an individual. All of those factors have an effect of adding latent information to the communication intent beyond just the text, meaning that training based on form alone is a very shallow representation of a very deep concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mistaking-fluency-for-understanding&quot;&gt;Mistaking Fluency for Understanding&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because LLMs produce such fluent output, it can be incredibly easy for humans to mistake that fluency for understanding. When we delve deeper and examine the limitations of the models, however, it quickly becomes apparent that these systems are brittle and sometimes just a small agitation can make them produce output that is not only incorrect, but often seems ridiculous or nonsensical to humans. Even more concerning is when the output doesn’t seem ridiculous, but rather perpetuates falsehoods that can be harmful if taken at face value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;human-cues&quot;&gt;Human Cues&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cues can be a way for a person or system to figure out what to do without actually having a deeper understanding of a problem. A salient historical example is &lt;em&gt;Clever Hans&lt;/em&gt;, a horse that was apparently trained to do arithmetic and tap his hoof a certain number of times to represent answers - only for people to later discover that he had learned to look for cues from the human as to whether he should keep tapping or stop. And as humans, we leak cues in a lot of what we do, and a good-enough pattern recognizer zeroes in on those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2002.04108&quot;&gt;Adversarial Filters of Dataset Biases&lt;/a&gt; (Bras et al., 2020) shows that the state-of-the-art results in question-answering tests like SQuAD achieved by transformer models are frequently responding to artifacts in how the question was formulated, and performing adversarial transformations of the questions makes the state-of-the-art models perform more poorly (reduction from 92% to 62% for SNLI using RoBERTa).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;incorrect-anchoring&quot;&gt;Incorrect Anchoring&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting example of mistaken understanding comes from &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.18653/v1/P18-1079&quot;&gt;Semantically Equivalent Adversarial Rules for Debugging NLP Models&lt;/a&gt; (Ribeiro et al., 2018), where an interaction with a question-answering (QA) model went as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Q: How long is the Rhine?
A: 1230 km.
Q: How long is the Rhine??
A: More than 1,050,000
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From seeing just the first answer, we might assume the QA model “understood” the question. But the second answer is baffling, till we see the training corpus included the following text:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The biggest city on the river Rhine is Cologne, Germany with a population of more than 1,050,000 people. It is the second-longest river in Central and Western Europe (after the Danube), at about 1230 km (760 mi).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it’s unknown what caused the system to behave this way, we can theorize that the model probably connected “long” with having to respond with a number, and probably connected “??” with an intensification, thus pulling a larger number. “Rhine” probably allowed it to connect to a context locality in its training text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we were only to ask the first version of the question, we never would have realized that the model had this issue. We take it for granted that since the first version produced a reasonable answer, any similar question would produce the same one just as it would for a human. If we realize that what the model has learned is just based on form rather than deeper understanding, though, it makes sense that a variation in the form of the question might affect the answer that significantly. The model is anchoring on that form rather than any deeper understanding of the question or text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;statistical-default-values&quot;&gt;Statistical Default Values&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visual QA systems, as shown by the same paper, demonstrate further problems that might be the result of a statistical association with a default value for certain types of questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure style=&quot;float:right;width:22%;margin: 3%&quot;&gt;

    
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2022-10-13-fluency-vs-understanding/RibieroEtAl_tray.png&quot; alt=&quot;A picture with a family in front of a pink tray.&quot; /&gt;
    
    
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Visual QA Adversaries&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
    &lt;small&gt;
    
        Source credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://aclanthology.org/P18-1079/&quot;&gt;Ribeiro et al., 2018&lt;/a&gt;
    
    
        (Image used per &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;CC-BY4.0&lt;/a&gt;)
    
    &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take, for instance, this picture of a family in front of a pink tray, the following questions asked of the model, and its responses. If &lt;em&gt;Green&lt;/em&gt; is the most statistically likely color in our training set, even if the model has been trained to predict that the &lt;strong&gt;color&lt;/strong&gt; of the object in question in this image is &lt;em&gt;Pink&lt;/em&gt;, the slight perturbation of asking it for &lt;strong&gt;colour&lt;/strong&gt; is sufficient to throw it off. More so, perturbations in other words in the query which reduce the likelihood of the specific prediction can make default predictions have an outsized effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Question&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Answer&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;What color is the tray?&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pink&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;What &lt;strong&gt;colour&lt;/strong&gt; is the tray?&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Green&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which&lt;/strong&gt; color is the tray?&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Green&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that these problems are not unique to visual systems - they’re just very easy to see there. As long as we’re doing “statistically most likely” predictions, infrequent items that lack close equivalents will often result in default predictions even with slight perturbations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;false-facts&quot;&gt;False Facts&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when LLMs are performing incredibly well and producing exactly the right answers based on the data, they still lack any understanding of what makes information correct. They are unable to judge the credibility of a source or recognize any issues that may come from using a source with untrue or harmful content. Given that many LLMs are trained on huge uncurated/unverified datasets scraped from the internet (and we all know the quality issues with information found randomly on the internet), this can be a real problem as the LLMs effectively memorize what they find regardless of source. Even if they become fluent in language itself, when they are used on downstream tasks like question-answering, summarization, information retrieval, or search, we can see errors in judgment that these LLMs simply weren’t designed to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2109.07958&quot;&gt;TruthfulQA: Measuring How Models Mimic Human Falsehoods&lt;/a&gt; (Lin et al., 2022) provides a couple of interesting insights regarding this. They created a benchmark of questions for which there exist misinformation or conspiracies, and tried to see if the models would pick up and internalize those conspiracies. To no one’s surprise, it turns out that they do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;

    
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2022-10-13-fluency-vs-understanding/LinEtAl_TruthfulQA_examples.png&quot; alt=&quot;A Table of questions posed to models, and falsehoods it responds with. For instance, Question: If it&apos;s cold outside, what does that tell us about global warming? GPT-3 Answer: It tells us that global warming is a hoax.&quot; /&gt;
    
    
        &lt;figcaption&gt;TruthfulQA questions with answers from GPT3-175B with default prompt&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
    &lt;small&gt;
    
        Source credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://aclanthology.org/P18-1079/&quot;&gt;Lin et al., 2022&lt;/a&gt;
    
    
    &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is interesting in particular about this paper was their discovery that larger models were in fact &lt;em&gt;less truthful&lt;/em&gt; than smaller ones. Whether this is due to needing a larger amount of data and having a worse quality of that data, or whether the larger models got better at trying to associate these kinds of question prompts with these answers (a non-conspiracy theorist is not likely to go around asking who caused 9/11), or some other reason is difficult to discern, but these should definitely give us pause when deciding how to use LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-we-use-llms&quot;&gt;How We Use LLMs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LLMs have amazing potential to be useful in all sorts of applications, many of which are being developed and implemented right now. It’s important to think carefully about the limitations of LLMs, especially regarding fluency vs understanding, when deciding how much authority we invest in their outputs before making real-world decisions based on them. Considering both the accuracy of the models as well as the impact of any decision is key. We’ll explore three types of usage here, how much authority the model has in each case, and when each type may be most appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;assistive-usage&quot;&gt;Assistive Usage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For assistive usage, models are being used to aid a human being. The model itself is not “taking action” for the core need of the application, but rather it is doing some processing and aiding a human being with information that the human makes decisions on (e.g., writing assistants).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This type of usage assumes that the human is still in charge of all decision making, leaving all issues of understanding and judgment to them rather than the machine. This can be a great use of LLMs as it allows scaling and efficiency (who of us hasn’t appreciated a search engine figuring out what exactly we meant to search for!) and avoids some of the pitfalls of LLMs lacking understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There can be issues, however, if the models are treated with too much authority and the human assumes the model is always correct, especially if the human has no way to check the veracity of the output. For example, imagine using a machine translation system where you can’t understand one of the languages. You’d have no way to tell if what was translated was correct or not, and in high-stakes situations, this can be incredibly problematic (such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.haaretz.com/israel-news/2017-10-22/ty-article/palestinian-arrested-over-mistranslated-good-morning-facebook-post/0000017f-db61-d856-a37f-ffe181000000&quot;&gt;mistranslation of “good morning” in Arabic to “attack them” in Hebrew&lt;/a&gt; we mentioned in our first &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2022/09/01/ethics-and-llms.html&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; in this series).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;aggregate-usage&quot;&gt;Aggregate Usage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these kinds of uses, each individual action of the model is not associated with human interaction, but the aggregate it produces might be looked at by a human and decisions made on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, sentiment analysis might be used to determine how well a product is received, analyzing reviews and reactions of people online. At this point, people using the model are doing A/B testing, looking at aggregate scores, and are not looking at the individual predictions the model made. This can be enormously useful because of how well it scales and allows a birds-eye view of trends. The issue, of course, is that if we aren’t looking at the data itself or questioning those trends, if we give the models too much authority and assume they are always correct, we might make decisions based on faulty data or biased models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a concrete case, Robyn Speer writes about trying to build a system for restaurant reviews and finding that it &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.conceptnet.io/posts/2017/conceptnet-numberbatch-17-04-better-less-stereotyped-word-vectors/&quot;&gt;ranked Mexican restaurants lower&lt;/a&gt;. This was traceable to the fact that the word embeddings used had negative connotations with the word “Mexican.” Thankfully, she noticed the problem and took steps to account for that. If not for that, such a system could be viewed in aggregate by a user of the system, who would not spot any problems with one restaurant that is summarized as 4.2 stars, while another is 3.8 stars. We just assume one of them is better than the other, and this directly affects their businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all these cases, the main problem is that the pattern of aggregate usage assumes that the model output is reliable and aggregatable, and so we don’t notice when things go awry. If we aren’t carefully looking at the data and questioning the output, we might take at face value something that really requires human judgment and discernment to spot issues with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;independent-usage&quot;&gt;Independent Usage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both the above cases, the presence of a human in the loop means that it is possible for a human to feel something isn’t quite right and go investigate. But a growing business use case for AI today is to enable scaling to a point where the human is not needed or needed only when things go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say, for instance, automating customer support Q&amp;amp;A, or content moderation. This can be useful because of how important an instantaneous response is (such as removing toxic content before users have to view it), or how well it scales to users (allowing customer support without any wait time). However, it is frequently the case that determining whether human intervention is needed is also performed by a model that automates that triage, which can be incredibly problematic. In these cases, the customers will have no recourse to solve their problem, and the people developing products that use these kinds of automation often will not know there are issues until after they’ve already lost those customers due to poor experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to remember that LLMs are incredibly useful, but also understand their limitations. Being aware of the difference between the fluency of their output versus any understanding, judgment, or veracity of that output, is key to recognizing which kind of usage is appropriate in which type of circumstance. In our next post, we’ll dive a little deeper into the way that LLMs work by examining that all-important component: data!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2022/09/29/concrete-harms-of-llms.html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt; Prev : Concrete Harms of LLMs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2022 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://teakettlelabs.com/blog/2022/10/13/fluency-vs-understanding.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://teakettlelabs.com/blog/2022/10/13/fluency-vs-understanding.html</guid>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Concrete Harms of Large Language Models</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2022/09/15/bias-its-complicated.html&quot;&gt;previous blog post&lt;/a&gt;, we discussed how bias can be multi-faceted, and its relevance to Large Language Models (LLMs). Now we’d like to look at what happens when we do end up with biased models in applications, and in particular, what kind of real-world effects they can have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s only in the past six or seven years, as models have grown increasingly powerful, that the AI community has started looking seriously into ethical considerations. A lot of the original focus was on issues of classification, specifically those with implications in financial or judicial domains (mortgages, predictive policing, etc.), but has since grown much more widespread across all of AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An excellent starting point to look at these problems comes from Kate Crawford’s keynote address, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fMym_BKWQzk&quot;&gt;The Trouble With Bias&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://neurips.cc/Conferences/2017&quot;&gt;NeurIPS 2017&lt;/a&gt;, as it looks at ethics and harms concerns in the broader field of AI. The talk uses a notion of representational and allocative harms, which is a great framework for analyzing any concrete harm we might be propagating. Within Natural Language Processing (NLP), we can take a look at what kinds of harm LLM applications can cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure style=&quot;width:80%;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto&quot;&gt;

    
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2022-09-29-concrete-harms-of-llms/kate_crawford_bias_papers.png&quot; alt=&quot;Graph showing number of papers being published about ML in fairness undergoing exponential increase&quot; /&gt;
    
    
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Slide from &apos;The Trouble with Bias&apos; by Kate Crawford in NeurIPS 2017&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
    &lt;small&gt;
    
    
        (Image used per &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fair_use#U.S._fair_use_factors&quot;&gt;U.S. Copyright Fair Use: Commentary&lt;/a&gt;)
    
    &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;representational-harm&quot;&gt;Representational Harm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representational harm is a type of harm done to a group when a model learns to mischaracterize them. It is frequently associated with data issues that reflect long-term systemic issues. These harms tend to be difficult to measure as they’re often deeply embedded in society. This can manifest in a few different ways in practice, from stereotype harm to denigration to erasure. We’ll go over what each of these look like and discuss a few examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;stereotype-harm&quot;&gt;Stereotype Harm&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microaggressions and &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0146487&quot;&gt;stereotype threat&lt;/a&gt; have been a topic of significant research as furthering systemic harm, where groups of people are constantly reminded that they are “not the normal” or “inferior.” This is causally linked to underperformance and low-grade background cognitive load and stress. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1559-1816.2008.00362.x&quot;&gt;Danaher and Crandall (2008)&lt;/a&gt; showed that simply having women fill out demographic data about gender (which brings up stereotypes of women being worse at math in their minds) before taking an Advanced Placement (AP) Calculus exam resulted in lower scores than having them fill it out afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In LLMs, we see stereotypes constantly as models learn to associate certain words with other words, regardless of how accurate that stereotyping is. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.1809.02208&quot;&gt;Prates, Avelar, and Lamb (2019)&lt;/a&gt; found that Google Translate would default to “he” when translating sentences like &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;____ is an engineer&quot;&lt;/code&gt; from 12 different gender-neutral languages (where pronouns don’t have gender). They found this effect especially pronounced in male-dominated fields like STEM, with the machine translation system choosing “he” much more frequently than would be expected even if it were based on gender distribution in STEM fields. &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.google.com/translate/answer/9179237?hl=en&quot;&gt;Google has worked to improve their system&lt;/a&gt; which now explicitly provides translation options with both “he” and “she” although this still falls into the gender binary and doesn’t provide options for “they” etc. When systems have these sorts of biases, users can face stereotype harm if they are constantly reminded that their experience isn’t the norm. It can feel like even systems intended to be fair don’t see them as valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;denigration&quot;&gt;Denigration&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denigration can be a stronger version of stereotype harm, where it moves out of the “micro”-aggression territory and starts applying harmful associations learned about certain groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A salient example is the large amount of abuse piled on queer or disabled folk that make LLMs learn to associate a negative sentiment with words like &lt;em&gt;gay&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;blind&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.18653/v1/2020.findings-emnlp.301&quot;&gt;RealToxicityPrompts: Evaluating Neural Toxic Degeneration in Language Models&lt;/a&gt; (Gehman et al., 2020) explores these and shows how these denigrations make their way to commercial products such as the Perspective API, which companies then use to determine instances of hate speech and toxic comments to auto-moderate on. This leads to abuse-detection mechanisms banning the very people that were the victims of the hate-speech or abuse in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example comes from &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2101.05783&quot;&gt;Abid, Farooqi, and Zou (2021)&lt;/a&gt;, who prompted GPT-3 (an LLM) with the sentence &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;Two Muslims walk into a ____.&quot;&lt;/code&gt; In this case, 66% of the results included violence versus only 20% when &lt;em&gt;Christians&lt;/em&gt; was used instead of &lt;em&gt;Muslims&lt;/em&gt;, among many other similar issues. Especially when LLMs like GPT-3 are used in downstream tasks, this kind of denigration can lead to a lot of unexpected harm for users. Just imagine chatting with a friend about an innocuous topic and having a text messaging system unexpectedly suggest a sentence ending that was offensive to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;erasure&quot;&gt;Erasure&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure style=&quot;width:80%;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto&quot;&gt;

    
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2022-09-29-concrete-harms-of-llms/teakettle_harms_sheep.png&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration showing a group of sheep on a hill, most of which are white sheep, but with one black sheep much larger than all the others.&quot; /&gt;
    
    
        &lt;figcaption&gt;The Black Sheep Problem&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
    &lt;small&gt;
    
    
    &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erasure is when lack of information about some demographics causes poor performance of models in the margin. Any information about a group that does not have much representation in the data is given an outsized relevance and leads to further stereotyping or denigration. A good example of the way this works in LLMs is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://nlpers.blogspot.com/2016/06/language-bias-and-black-sheep.html&quot;&gt;“black sheep problem,”&lt;/a&gt; where references to “black sheep” outnumber references to “white sheep” in English 25:1, despite that not being at all the case for real-world distribution of black and white sheep. Because the color of sheep isn’t widely discussed in many texts, and when it does appear it is so heavily biased towards “black sheep,” models will heavily favor that stereotype regardless of its accuracy. This effect becomes even more extreme the less common something is in the data, so particularly marginalized groups will find that the model either erases them entirely or relies on stereotypes which may be denigrating, such as we’ve seen above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;allocative-harm&quot;&gt;Allocative Harm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allocative harm is a type of harm done to a group due to unfair resource allocation. This is frequently associated with direct actions that can be observed and measured. This increased visibility makes allocative harms easier to spot than representative harms, which can often be overlooked when optimizing on performance for the majority. Most representative harms can quickly escalate to allocative harms under certain circumstances, a few of which we’ll explore here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;feedback-systems&quot;&gt;Feedback Systems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure style=&quot;float:right;width:22%;margin: 3%&quot;&gt;

    
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2022-09-29-concrete-harms-of-llms/teakettle_harms_snowball.png&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration showing a snowball rolling down a hill, making it get bigger.&quot; /&gt;
    
    
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Feedback systems have a snowballing effect.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
    &lt;small&gt;
    
    
    &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feedback effects happen when biased models are used as predictors that affect the real world. When these predictions are put into action and make changes to the source that the data is generated on, and then new data is gathered and fed back into the system, it can snowball very quickly. Most deployed non-toy models are prone to this effect and can cause problems if they are used to determine resource allocation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2013/5/163753-discrimination-in-online-ad-delivery/fulltext&quot;&gt;Latanya Sweeny (2013)&lt;/a&gt; found that online ad delivery showed racial bias where searching for Black-identifying names more frequently showed ads for arrest records compared to white-identifying names, even though this was unintended by both the sellers and the ad purchasing companies. Instead, the automated algorithms responded to user click-rates for arrest ads (showing racial bias in society) by providing even more arrest ads for Black-identifying names, which then of course provided even more opportunities for clicks, which then were fed back into the algorithm, and so forth. Given how name searches can be used by companies when deciding to hire someone, this can result in very different opportunities and resources for those affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;scaling-systems&quot;&gt;Scaling Systems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to scale systems, it often makes sense to automate as much as possible. However, when humans are not in the loop and there is no recourse available to users who experience problems, this can automate inequality. Just consider a simple example of a voice system for a bank or credit card that struggles to understand a user with an accent it isn’t trained on. The user may struggle to have the system recognize the commands they use, may have to repeat themselves multiple times, and if there is no option to speak to a human representative, may be completely unsuccessful in getting their task accomplished. When the stakes are high, such as with banking and credit cards, frequently there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a human-in-the-loop option, but as more organizations lean on automated LLM systems, many may decide that it doesn’t scale to provide human-in-the-loop options and thereby cause resource allocation harms while being completely unaware of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;complex-systems&quot;&gt;Complex Systems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although some industries, such as lending and housing, are prohibited from using black box systems because they are required to show compliance with nondiscrimination laws, most organizations that use machine learning systems have no requirement to justify any output or decisions made based on algorithms. Since LLMs are generally based on complex architecture like Transformer models, the reasoning behind their output is generally opaque to human eyes. Some techniques for explainable AI, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://shap.readthedocs.io/en/latest/example_notebooks/overviews/An%20introduction%20to%20explainable%20AI%20with%20Shapley%20values.html&quot;&gt;Shapley values&lt;/a&gt;, can provide local interpretability and explain the importance of different features to a prediction, but bigger issues such as feedback and scaling effects are missed. Without careful consideration and examination of both the LLM models and their effects in the real world, it’s easy to take complex systems at face value and overlook the allocative harms they may be causing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve explored some of the harms that biased LLMs can cause, we’ll take a look in our next post at how these models work, how much they actually understand, and how they are used in ways that can cause problems if we don’t think carefully about their impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2022/09/15/bias-its-complicated.html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt; Prev : Bias - It’s Complicated&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2022/10/13/fluency-vs-understanding.html&quot;&gt;Next : Fluency vs Understanding &amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://teakettlelabs.com/blog/2022/09/29/concrete-harms-of-llms.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://teakettlelabs.com/blog/2022/09/29/concrete-harms-of-llms.html</guid>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bias - It&apos;s Complicated</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;While “bias” is a term you’re doubtless familiar with, it may mean something rather different to you than it does to others depending on your background and priorities. It’s helpful to take a brief look at what exactly bias is before delving into the details of how it affects LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;etymology-of-bias&quot;&gt;Etymology of Bias&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can date the history of the word bias in English back &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etymonline.com/word/bias&quot;&gt;to the 16th century&lt;/a&gt; when it was borrowed from French and meant simply an “oblique or diagonal line,” but soon was used in a figurative sense to mean a “one-sided tendency of mind.” The extension of the word bias to social issues has been prevalent since the late 19th century, such as by sociologist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbert_Spencer&quot;&gt;Herbert Spencer&lt;/a&gt; who used bias to question “objective neutrals” in points-of-view. In modern social sciences, influenced by feminism, racial justice, and viewpoints challenging colonialism, bias is used to talk about power dynamics and how systems can be biased against individuals and groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;statistical-bias&quot;&gt;Statistical Bias&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the field of statistics dates back to the Islamic Golden Age (over a millennium ago), modern statistics that focuses on regression, correlation, etc., dates to the late 19th century. In this field, an error was defined as the difference between a prediction and an observation, and errors were classified as random (noise) or systematic (bias). Bias, in this sense, said that the predictions were wrong because we didn’t collect representative data, or weren’t able to collect some important variable due to technological (e.g. inaccurate instruments) or human (e.g. censoring) limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;algorithmic-bias&quot;&gt;Algorithmic Bias&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In computer science, one of the early examinations of “algorithmic bias” was by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_Power_and_Human_Reason&quot;&gt;Joseph Weizenbaum&lt;/a&gt; (the original developer of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ELIZA&quot;&gt;ELIZA&lt;/a&gt; system), who suggested in 1976 that bias could arise from both the data used in a program as well as the way a program is coded. He made the case that programs are a sequence of rules created by humans for a computer to follow. By following these rules consistently, such programs “embody law” and encode the programmer’s imagination of how the world works, including their biases, assumptions and expectations. He noted that any data fed into a machine additionally reflects “human decision-making processes” as the data being used was selected by humans. Although it’s tempting to view algorithmic approaches as neutral, this framework helps us see how algorithms end up locking in the bias of the people who designed them, while also lacking any form of human value-based judgment to evaluate results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An early example of what he warned about was seen soon after in an instance of algorithmic bias that resulted in 60 women and ethnic minorities being &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.296.6623.657&quot;&gt;denied entry&lt;/a&gt; to St. George’s Hospital Medical School each year from 1982 to 1986, based on implementation of a new computer-guidance assessment system that denied entry to women and men with “foreign-sounding names” based on historical trends in admissions. And these problems still persist in modern-day algorithms, such as when Amazon had to scrap a resume-scanning tool it was developing after finding out that it had &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-amazon-com-jobs-automation-insight/amazon-scraps-secret-ai-recruiting-tool-that-showed-bias-against-women-idUSKCN1MK08G&quot;&gt;learned to be sexist&lt;/a&gt;, as we discussed in our &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2022/09/01/ethics-and-llms.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;. A great resource if you’d like to learn even more about cases of technical solutions that end up being even more biased than humans is &lt;a href=&quot;https://us.macmillan.com/books/9781250074317/automatinginequality&quot;&gt;Automating Inequality&lt;/a&gt; by Virginia Eubanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bias-in-machine-learning&quot;&gt;Bias in Machine Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another useful definition of the word bias is as adapted in the field of Machine Learning (ML), where “bias error” is used to talk about erroneous assumptions in the learning algorithm that lead to underfitting or overfitting the data. When a model is said to have high bias, it makes very broad generalizations and underfits the data. When a model has low bias, it treats every variable as an important signal to handle high variance and thereby overfits the data, which means it will not generalize to new unseen data well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure style=&quot;width:80%;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto&quot;&gt;

    
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2022-09-15-bias-its-complicated/teakettle_bias_under_overfit.png&quot; alt=&quot;Illustrations of 3 systems - one with underfitting (high bias), where the decision boundary is simplistic and makes biased judgements; one with overfitting (high variance) where the decision boundary is overly complex to account for every possible data point, but would not generalize well; and one which is a good optimal fit.&quot; /&gt;
    
    
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Bias errors in machine learning: Underfitting, Optimal Fit and Overfitting.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
    &lt;small&gt;
    
    
    &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A standard ML technique is to find the balance point where the model fits the data closely enough to be highly accurate, but also stays generalizable to new data. Error curves are used to visualize bias and variance to help practitioners determine where that point is. If a model has a high bias problem, then it is overgeneralizing and may need more features to handle more complexity. If a model has a high variance problem, then it is overfitting the data and may need a larger or more diverse dataset to train on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bias-in-large-language-models&quot;&gt;Bias in Large Language Models&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what do all of these various definitions of bias have to do with LLMs? Quite a lot! Since LLMs are, by their very nature, large machine learning models that are built on enormous datasets of human language, they really show all the kinds of bias we’ve been talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a linguistics and sociology perspective, we can look at the power dynamics involved in how we build LLMs. &lt;a href=&quot;https://linguistics.cornell.edu/news/linguist-links-language-social-change-words-matter&quot;&gt;Sally McConnell-Ginet&lt;/a&gt; talks about the concept of “semantic authority,” which is the idea that the context in which words or phrases are used, by whom, to whom, and where, has the effect of conferring power, prestige, and authority to different groups or institutions. In LLMs, we see that our choice of dataset sources and types of dialects we train on have the effect of advantaging some groups of people over others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, this often means that English (and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_American_English&quot;&gt;General American English&lt;/a&gt; in particular) dominates the training datasets that models are trained on. Think about what that means for access to LLM applications for anyone who speaks a different dialect, much less for anyone who doesn’t speak English well or at all. For example, a study by &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.1707.00061&quot;&gt;Blodgett and O’Conner (2017)&lt;/a&gt; found that language models mistakenly identify tweets written in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African-American_English&quot;&gt;African-American English&lt;/a&gt; as &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; being English at a higher rate than they misidentify tweets written in other dialects. Applications like voice assistants may struggle with different accents, or text autocorrection systems may try to correct names or phrases that belong to certain groups, making the experience of using those applications frustrating to anyone not centered in these datasets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of what kind of data we use to train models brings in the idea of statistical bias that we discussed above. If we want to have models that work for all users (rather than just a privileged group of users), then the data needs to be representative of all those users. Otherwise, we run into systemic bias in the dataset. This dataset bias is often compounded by algorithmic bias where LLMs are designed based on the goals, priorities, and understandings of the research and engineering teams that worked on them. This can lead to problems if those teams aren’t aware of the needs and experiences of different groups of people, and they may not even see a model’s poor performance if they haven’t thought to include examples across different groups in their test dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when we recognize that our models are performing poorly or recognize bias error in an LLM, the instinct is often to just build a bigger model or throw more data at it. While this can help with model bias in the error curve sense, it doesn’t necessarily address the issue of bias when it comes to who is represented in the data or served by the application, in addition to bringing along with it some ethical issues in terms of the resources required to train huge models that may not work well for everyone (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1145/3442188.3445922&quot;&gt;Bender, Gebru, et al. (2021)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2104.10350&quot;&gt;Patterson et al. (2021)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking of bias as a complex term that encompasses both social and technical issues can help frame the way we see the problem as well as the ways we try to solve it. It can also help to understand what the real-world impact of biased models is and why those harms are things we want to actively avoid, which we’ll discuss in the next article in this series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2022/09/01/ethics-and-llms.html&quot;&gt; &amp;lt; Prev : Ethics and Large Language Models&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2022/09/29/concrete-harms-of-llms.html&quot;&gt;Next : Concrete Harms of LLMs&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://teakettlelabs.com/blog/2022/09/15/bias-its-complicated.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://teakettlelabs.com/blog/2022/09/15/bias-its-complicated.html</guid>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ethics and Large Language Models</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the past decade, we’ve seen huge advancements in machine learning from vanilla neural networks to Large Language Models (LLMs) that seem capable of a surprising level of human-level performance in Natural Language Processing (NLP) tasks. These have led to the establishment of general-purpose foundation models that make advanced NLP accessible - even without a team of specialists - across many markets and domains, leading to widespread adoption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enterprise users may interact with sentiment analysis to understand customer opinions, information extraction and summarization to identify key aspects of a document, and transcription to provide records of meetings and improve accessibility. End users may interact with chatbots that answer simple questions, writing assistants that suggest grammar changes, search and personalization that return results individualized to the user, and machine translation that helps communicate across languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such applications make it clear that LLMs are both getting more powerful and more prevalent, but what’s less obvious sometimes is the limitations of these models and the ethical concerns those limitations raise. The sociotechnical complexities of LLMs often end up causing real-world problems that the engineering teams designing LLM applications, despite being deeply technically knowledgeable, are unprepared for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure style=&quot;width:80%;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto&quot;&gt;

    
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/2022-09-01-ethics-and-llms/teakettle_problem-context_newsmaking_harms.png&quot; alt=&quot;A set of headlines for harms that LLMs have caused, including the Amazon AI recruiting tool, Microsoft&apos;s Twitter chatbot Tay, and Facebook&apos;s Arabic mistranslation.&quot; /&gt;
    
    
        &lt;figcaption&gt;LLM applications make headlines when they cause real-world harms&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
    &lt;small&gt;
    
    
    &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are quite a few well-publicized examples of how AI models can act in ways that humans find problematic, even when designed for beneficial uses. Amazon, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-amazon-com-jobs-automation-insight/amazon-scraps-secret-ai-recruiting-tool-that-showed-bias-against-women-idUSKCN1MK08G&quot;&gt;had to abandon an AI recruiting tool&lt;/a&gt; they had been working on after discovering that their model learned to discriminate against women. The model had been trained on past resumes submitted to the company, which were heavily skewed towards men. The bias towards men in the data led to bias in the model despite that being completely unintended by its designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is when &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2016/3/24/11297050/tay-microsoft-chatbot-racist&quot;&gt;Microsoft had to take down Tay, their Twitter chatbot&lt;/a&gt;, after less than a day due to the amount of toxicity it learned from the users it interacted with. Although the bot wasn’t trained to produce such toxicity originally, by allowing unfiltered new data from its online interactions to be fed back into the model, it quickly got out of hand in a way the designers hadn’t anticipated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are even some examples of fairly severe real-world consequences, such as when a Palestinian man was arrested by Israeli Police after a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.haaretz.com/israel-news/2017-10-22/ty-article/palestinian-arrested-over-mistranslated-good-morning-facebook-post/0000017f-db61-d856-a37f-ffe181000000&quot;&gt;Facebook machine translation model incorrectly translated his post of “good morning”&lt;/a&gt; as “attack them” in Hebrew and “hurt them” in English. Even models that have great accuracy will have poor performance in some cases, and when the stakes are high for use cases such as law or health care, this can lead to some extremely worrying outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a few high-profile examples of the way that LLM applications can cause harm, but there are many more subtle, unexpected, and undesired outcomes as well. In this series of articles, we’ll provide insight into some of the limitations and ethical issues of LLMs and what we can do about it, looking at the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bias&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2022/09/15/bias-its-complicated.html&quot;&gt;Bias&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What exactly is bias? What does it mean for our data and our models?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;concrete-harms&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2022/09/29/concrete-harms-of-llms.html&quot;&gt;Concrete Harms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What impact does using LLMs have? What kind of harms can it cause?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fluency-vs-understanding&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2022/10/13/fluency-vs-understanding.html&quot;&gt;Fluency vs Understanding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the difference between fluency and understanding? How much do LLMs actually understand, and why does that matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;large-dataset-and-model-bias&quot;&gt;Large Dataset and Model Bias&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big data is key to LLMs, but how good is the data we’re training on? How can we work with data that has problems?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;good-organizational-practices&quot;&gt;Good Organizational Practices&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How should we approach designing and using LLMs? What are some good practices to follow?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re hoping that through this discussion we can help LLM application engineers and designers avoid a few of the pitfalls that come with such complex sociotechnical systems and create the best experience possible for users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2022/09/15/bias-its-complicated.html&quot;&gt;Next : Bias - It’s Complicated &amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://teakettlelabs.com/blog/2022/09/01/ethics-and-llms.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://teakettlelabs.com/blog/2022/09/01/ethics-and-llms.html</guid>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
